<?xml version="1.0"?>
<page title="The Last Craft?" here="Last Craft">
    <long_title>
        The Last Craft? Web developer tutorials on PHP, Extreme programming
        and Object Oriented development
    </long_title>
    <content>
        <introduction>
            <p>
                This site focuses mostly on developing with lightweight web technologies such as
                <a href="http://www.php.net/">PHP</a>,
                especially when applied with agile methodologies such as
                <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/">XP</a>.
                No guarantee of quality is given or even intended.
                It is hoped only that what you find gives you ideas and enthusiasm
                from a fellow computer programmer.
            </p>
        </introduction>
        <section name="what" title="Ongoing projects">
            <p>
                My wife is going to kill me, but I've just started another
                Sourceforge project.
                It's a requirents testing and sign-off tool called
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/arbiter">Arbiter</a>.
                It's actually best described in this
                <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/forums/showthread.php?t=193797">Sitepoint thread</a>,
                but basically think of it as a document driven FIT for small
                web projects only.
                The project is currently stalled while I finish the first version
                of SimpleTest, but should resume shortly.
            </p>
            <p>
                Along with Jon Ramsey, Matt Jones and Demian Turner, I am involved in
                <a href="http://www.phplondon.org/wiki/">PHP London</a>, a PHP user
                group not surprisingly based in London.
                It is early days, but going well.
                Given the large number of PHP developers and
                businesses in the London area it should have every chance of success.
                The networking meetings take place on the first Thursday of every month.
                In addition the group organises various visits and also a
                <a href="http://www.phplondon.org/wiki/CodeFest2005January29">code fest</a>.
                A spin off from the code fest is a
                <a href="http://souceforge.net/projects/spamproofwiki/">spam proof wiki</a>
            </p>
            <p>
                The <a local="simple_test">SimpleTest PHP unit tester</a> has finally hit the
				1.0 mark and is available for download from your nearest <a 
				href="http://souceforge.net/projects/simpletest/">SourceForge</a>.
                It is a PHP unit test and web test framework that has been built
                to be extensible in various ways.
                Users of <a href="http://www.junit.org/">JUnit</a> will be
                familiar with most of the interface.
                The test display is customisable as well as the base test
                case and in addition the mock objects can be used with other unit
                testers.
                <a href="http://jwebunit.sourceforge.net/">JWebUnit</a>
                style functionality is more complete now.
                It has support for SSL, frames, proxies, basic authentication and a wider
                range of HTML controls.
                The idea is that common but fiddly PHP tasks, such as logging into a site,
                can be tested easily.
            </p>
            <p>
                Also on the subject of open source, <a href="http://www.wordtracker.com/">Wordtracker</a>
                have kindly agreed to publish some of their in house tools.
                The first of these was a lightweight persistence library.
                Written in PHP, it is built around the <em>UnitOfWork</em> pattern
                rather than the notion of persistence.
                The idea is that being short lived, PHP scripts affect a change on
                an object model rather handle in memeory objects that happen to know
                how to survive requests.
                So far it has only been published in
                <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/forums/showthread.php?t=214183">this SitePoint thread</a>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Another Wordtracker spin off is
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/fakemail/">FakeMail</a>.
                Testing applications that send e-mails can be a right royal pain because
                of all of the infrastructure involved.
                You will likely need an SMPT gateway that talks to a POP client that
                you can read the queue from.
                That's a lot of set up.
                Fakemail acts as an SMTP gateway on any port you define.
                When you send it a mail it simply copies that mail to the local file
                system in whatever directory you want.
                You then just have to look at the local file.
                It means that you must be able to configure your application to use
                a port other than 25, but that's not usualy difficult.
                Documentation is lacking, but it's just a simple Perl script.
            </p>
            <p>
                Yet another sourceforge project I am contributing to is
                <a href="http://www.buennagel.com/">Jochen Buennagel&apos;s</a>
                <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/phpduploc/">PHP::Duploc</a>.
                It is a tool for visualising repetition in code so as to
                identify targets for refactoring.
                One file goes on the X-axis and another on the Y-axis...
                <br />
                <img src="images/dotplot.png"/>
                <br />
                Any similar lines are marked with a dot and the patterns
                produced can be read to spot areas of suspect design.
                A bit like reading tealeaves and a lot of fun.
                It could even be useful.
            </p>
            <p>
                I now have a blog of course!
                Gives me a chance to rehash old
                <a href="http://www.sitepoint.com/forums/forumdisplay.php?f=147">Sitepoint</a>
                postings where I feel I had something to say, and to rant occasionally.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="why" title="Why the Last Craft?">
            <p>
                A craft is defined as...
                <div class="quotation">
                    Art or skill; dexterity in particular manual employment;
                    hence, the occupation or employment itself; manual art; a
                    trade.
                </div>
            </p>
            <p>
                If you lose a screw or clasp from a hand made jewellery box it is hopeless to
                try to find a replacement. Nothing else is quite the same and the mechanism will
                fail to work. It may even cause more damage when applied. You need to find the original maker
                or someone of the same skill to make you another.
                Sound like software?
                Yet mechanical parts today are interchangeable.
            </p>
            <p>
                Writing software has resisted mass production.
                As soon as a part of it becomes
                routine it can be automated.
                Once it is you don&apos;t need a programmer any more.
                Routine programming jobs no longer exist.
                All that is left is the unsolved problems that require
                a higher level of skill in constructing their solutions.
            </p>
            <p>
                This dependency on the ability of the artisan, combined with nothing quite fitting
                together properly, is what gives software the pre-industrial feel.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="rrc" title="The cards?">
            <p>
                The panel at the top is supposed to resemble a standard office index card.
                The way it is marked out is called an
                <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0201379430/ref=lib_dp_TFCV/102-1207283-8247304?v=glance&amp;s=books&amp;vi=reader#reader-link">RRC card</a>.
                It stands for Roles, Responsibilities and
                Collaborations and is the cheapest software development tool you
                can find.
                You really do buy a pack of cards.
            <p>
            </p>
                The role is written at the top and would often be just a class
                name (they are usually called
                <a href="http://www.c2.com/doc/crc/draw.html">CRC cards</a>
                in this case).
                The left side is the object&apos;s responsibilities and on the
                right collaborations (within the page I have treated these as
                internal links and external links repectively).
                A group of developers can point at, discuss and discard cards
                in the heat of design session.
                It makes it especially difficult for only one person to take charge
                of a discussion in the way you can with a UML tool or notepad.
                Try scribbling out five cards before someone gets a look in.
            </p>
            <p>
                Now nothing beats a whiteboard for collaboration, but if the level
                of detail is getting too high and you want a temporary record,
                give the RRC cards a try.
            </p>
        </section>
    </content>
    <internal>
        <link>
            <a href="#what">Projects</a> under development.
            All free and open source software.
        </link>
        <link>
            <a href="#why">Why Last Craft?</a>
            Odd name isn&apos;t it?
        </link>
        <link>
            <a href="#rrc">Why this index card</a> at the top?
        </link>
    </internal>
    <external>
        <link>
            <a local="simple_test">SimpleTest</a> is a PHP unit test framework.
        </link>
        <link>
            My article on <a href="http://www.developerspot.com/tutorials/php/test-driven-development/page1.html">TDD</a>
        </link>
        <link>
            My article on the
            <a href="http://www.phppatterns.com/index.php/article/articleview/75/1/1/">Registry Pattern</a>.
        </link>
        <link>
            Site E-mail is
            <a href="http://spamcop.net">SpamCop</a>
            filtered which I cannot recommend enough.
        </link>
    </external>
    <meta>
        <keywords>
            software development,
            computer programmer,
            php programming,
            programming php,
            software development tools,
            software development company,
            php tutorial,
            free php scripts,
            bespoke software development uk,
            corporate web development,
            architecture,
            php resources,
            wordtracker,
            xslt,
            java,
            bug tracker,
            bug reporting,
            unit test,
            php testing,
            test cases tutorial,
            explain unit test case,
            unit test example,
            xml
        </keywords>
        <description>
            A web site of software development tutorials and examples with an
            emphasis on web programming, testing, agile methodology and PHP
            development
        </description>
    </meta>
</page>